<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Sébastien Brisard's blog</title>
    <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/</link>

    <item>
      <title>New paper out!</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20170223-New_paper_out.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20170223-New_paper_out.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Febr 2017</pubDate>
      <description>My paper “Towards improved Hashin--Shtrikman bounds on the effective moduli of random composites” has recently been published in Mechanics & Industry.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 8: estimating the correlations</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20160627-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-08.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20160627-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-08.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 June 2016</pubDate>
      <description>In the previous instalment of this series, we have analyzed the morphology of the rice grains. In particular, we have defined their /orientation/ as that of the major axis of inertia. We are now in a position to quantify the statistics of the orientations. We will first discuss one-point statistics (each grain is considered individually), then two-point statistics (mutual orientations of pairs of grains are considered). Finally, we will try to quantify how the wall of the sample container influences the orientation of the rice grains.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New paper</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20160613-New_paper.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20160613-New_paper.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 June 2016</pubDate>
      <description>My paper “Reconstructing displacements from the solution to the periodic Lippmann–Schwinger equation discretized on a uniform grid” has recently been published in International Journal of Numerical Methods in Engineering.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 7: analysis of the shape of the grains</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20160219-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-07.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20160219-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-07.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Febr 2016</pubDate>
      <description>In the previous instalment of this series, we have segmented the 3D image of the assembly of rice grains. In other words, each voxel of the image is attributed the label of the grain to which it belongs. Remember the initial goal of this series: we want to quantify orientation correlations between grains. To do so, we must analyse the orientation of each individual grain. This is the topic of the present post.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New paper published</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20151208-New_paper_published.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20151208-New_paper_published.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 8 Dec 2015</pubDate>
      <description>My student Vinh Phuc Tran has recently had one of his papers published in Mechanics of Materials. The paper is called Stochastic modeling of mesoscopic elasticity random field.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 6: segmentation</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150930-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-06.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150930-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-06.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sept 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In the previous instalment of this series, I showed that a convincing binary image could be produced from the gray level 3D reconstruction of the assembly of rice grains, using Otsu's threshold. However, I intend to carry out statistical analyses of the grains themselves in the subsequent instalments. Therefore, instead of a binary image of the rice grains, what is really needed is a labelled image, where all voxels which are thought to belong to the same rice grain are tagged with the same label. This is called segmentation, which is the topic of the present post. I will first show that the most basic segmentation technique (namely, detecting connected components in the image) fails in the present case. This calls for a more elaborate strategy, based on the widely popular watershed method. However, blind application of the standard watershed strategy leads to over-segmentation. This post will therefore close on a problem-dependent strategy better suited to the present case.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 5: thresholding</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150709-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-05.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150709-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-05.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 9 July 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In the previous instalment of this series, we used the circle Hough transform to find the boundary of the sample and define the circular ROI. Within this ROI, we now need to segment the rice grains. In other words, starting from a gray-level image (Fig. 1, left), we want to produce a binary image, where all pixels that we believe belong to rice grains are white, and all background pixels are black (Fig. 1, right). This is the topic of the present post, where we will use Otsu's automated threshold selection. I will first discuss Otsu's method, and propose what I believe is a new interpretation of this rather old technique. Then, I will apply this method to the 3D image of rice grains, using scikit-image.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When a thin shell is not so thin, part 3: the thick shell solution</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150706-When_a_thin_shell_is_not_so_thin-03.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150706-When_a_thin_shell_is_not_so_thin-03.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 6 July 2015</pubDate>
      <description>
        Finding the stress resultant and stress couple in a spherical pressure vessel seems easy enough. Well, this apparently simple problem allows us to highlight subtle thickness effects within shells. It should be emphasized again that these thickness effects have nothing to do with shear corrections. Indeed, shear stresses are null at any point of the spherical pressure vessel. Rather, the thickness effects we are discussing in this series are due to curvature.

        In the first instalment of this series, I showed that using Koiter's thin shell solution leads to a non-null stress couple, which came as quite a surprise. In the second instalment, I used the exact, 3D solution to derive reference values of the stress couple and stress resultant through integration over the thickness of the shell. In particular, I showed that thickness corrections had to be incorporated.

        This still does not settle the matter, since the results obtained within the framework of Koiter's thin shell theory (see first instalment) are inconsistent with the reference, 3D elasticity values (see second instalment). To reconcile both approaches (3D elasticity vs. shell theory), we need to use a thick shell theory, as illustrated below.
      </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When a thin shell is not so thin, part 2: the 3D, exact solution</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150701-When_a_thin_shell_is_not_so_thin-02.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150701-When_a_thin_shell_is_not_so_thin-02.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 1 July 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In the previous instalment of this series, we analysed a spherical pressure vessel by means of Koiter's linear theory of thin shells. We found the somewhat unexpected result that the stress couple was not null. Besides, we also found that the stress resultant was slightly different from the well-known value \(N=pR/2\). So what was wrong with the previous analysis? To explore this question, we will make use of the exact solution in 3D elasticity.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This blog is now licensed!</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150701-This_blog_is_now_licensed.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150701-This_blog_is_now_licensed.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 1 July 2015</pubDate>
      <description>As indicated at the bottom of each page of this website, this blog is now licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License. This means that you are free to share and/or adapt the contents of this blog, as long as you give appropriate credit to the author. You may not make profit out of this website, though.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When a thin shell is not so thin, part 1: Koiter's linear theory</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150608-When_a_thin_shell_is_not_so_thin-01.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150608-When_a_thin_shell_is_not_so_thin-01.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 8 June 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In structural analysis, thick beams (resp. plates) usually refer to shear deformability, and the Timoshenko beam theory (resp. Mindlin–Reissner plate theory). With curved elements however (e.g. curved beams or shells), the situation is more subtle, as thickness corrections may be necessary even in shells /where the shear stress is null at any point/. In this series, this is illustrated with a spherical pressure vessel, for which the stress resultants and couples are studied. "Easy enough", you probably think: N=pR/2, M=0 and that's the end of it. Well, maybe...</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 4: defining the ROI</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150529-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-04.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150529-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-04.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In the previous instalment of this series, we obtained binned slices of the sample. Fig. 1 is a typical example of these binned slices. We now want to segment the rice grains. However, the analysis (in particular, Otsu thresholding) might be perturbed by the fact that the walls of the sample container are visible on the 3D image. In this post, I will show how we can locate these walls. Then, any subsequent analysis will be performed within the Region Of Interest (ROI) thus defined.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 3: intermezzo – Binning images</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150330-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-03.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150330-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-03.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015</pubDate>
      <description>The full reconstructed image resulting from the tomography experiment described in the second instalment of this series is a 1747×1751×688 stack. The voxel size is about 0.030 mm. This is far too much for the purpose of the present study, since all we are interested in is the determination of the location (coordinates of the centroid) and orientation (principal axes of inertia) of the rice grains. In order to reduce the computation time, the images will first be binned, that is each set of (say) 4×4×4 voxels will be replaced with a unique voxel, with average gray value (see Fig. 1 below for an illustration). 3D binning would usually require 3 uggly nested loops. There is, however, a much more pythonic way. This is the topic of the present post.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 2: acquisition of tomography images</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150310-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-02.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150310-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-02.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In the <a href="http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150223-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-01.html">first</a> instalment of this series, I briefly introduced orientational order in assemblies of anisotropic particles, and proposed an illustration based on synthetic microstructures. But what I really intend to do in this series is to show how orientational order can be quantified in a "real-life" sample, namely a packing of rice grains. This of course requires a 3D image of the packing. Fortunately, my lab (<a href="http://navier.enpc.fr/">Laboratoire Navier</a>) is the proud host of a <a href="http://navier.enpc.fr/Microtomographe,297">collaborative microtomography platform</a> and my former colleague Nicolas Lenoir --who was in charge of this instrument-- gave me the opportunity to scan my toy sample in december 2013.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 1: introduction</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150223-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-01.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150223-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-01.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In this series, I will explore the notion of orientational order in random packings of anisotropic (flat or elongated), hard particles. By orientational order, I mean that particles which are close to each other tend to adopt the same orientation. This leads to strong /local/ anisotropy, while the packing may well be /globally/ isotropic; in particular, all orientations of single grains are equiprobable. Local orientational order is stronger when the volume fraction of particles, or their aspect ratio increases.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Blog!</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20141219-New_Blog.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20141219-New_Blog</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2014</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of "Parallel Programming with Python"</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20140813-Review_of_Parallel_Programming_with_Python.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20140813-Review_of_Parallel_Programming_with_Python.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2014</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The periodic Green operator for strains</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20140306-The_periodic_Green_operator_for_strains.html</link>
      <guid>The_periodic_Green_operator_for_strains.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 6 Mar 2014</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decomposition of transverse isotropic, fourth-rank tensors</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20140226-Decomposition_of_transverse_isotropic_fourth-rank_tensors.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20140226-Decomposition_of_transverse_isotropic_fourth-rank_tensors.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2014</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the double dot product</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20140219-On_the_double_dot_product.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20140219-On_the_double_dot_product.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
