<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Sébastien Brisard's blog</title>
    <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/</link>
    <item>
      <title>When a thin shell is not so thin, part 2: the 3D, exact solution</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150701-When_a_thin_shell_is_not_so_thin-02.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150701-When_a_thin_shell_is_not_so_thin-02.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 1 July 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In the previous instalment of this series, we analysed a spherical pressure vessel by means of Koiter's linear theory of thin shells. We found the somewhat unexpected result that the stress couple was not null. Besides, we also found that the stress resultant was slightly different from the well-known value \(N=pR/2\). So what was wrong with the previous analysis? To explore this question, we will make use of the exact solution in 3D elasticity.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This blog is now licensed!</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150701-This_blog_is_now_licensed.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150701-This_blog_is_now_licensed.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 1 July 2015</pubDate>
      <description>As indicated at the bottom of each page of this website, this blog is now licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License. This means that you are free to share and/or adapt the contents of this blog, as long as you give appropriate credit to the author. You may not make profit out of this website, though.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When a thin shell is not so thin, part 1: Koiter's linear theory</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150608-When_a_thin_shell_is_not_so_thin-01.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150608-When_a_thin_shell_is_not_so_thin-01.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 8 June 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In structural analysis, thick beams (resp. plates) usually refer to shear deformability, and the Timoshenko beam theory (resp. Mindlin–Reissner plate theory). With curved elements however (e.g. curved beams or shells), the situation is more subtle, as thickness corrections may be necessary even in shells /where the shear stress is null at any point/. In this series, this is illustrated with a spherical pressure vessel, for which the stress resultants and couples are studied. "Easy enough", you probably think: N=pR/2, M=0 and that's the end of it. Well, maybe...</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 4: defining the ROI</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150529-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-04.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150529-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-04.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In the previous instalment of this series, we obtained binned slices of the sample. Fig. 1 is a typical example of these binned slices. We now want to segment the rice grains. However, the analysis (in particular, Otsu thresholding) might be perturbed by the fact that the walls of the sample container are visible on the 3D image. In this post, I will show how we can locate these walls. Then, any subsequent analysis will be performed within the Region Of Interest (ROI) thus defined.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 3: intermezzo – Binning images</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150330-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-03.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150330-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-03.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015</pubDate>
      <description>The full reconstructed image resulting from the tomography experiment described in the second instalment of this series is a 1747×1751×688 stack. The voxel size is about 0.030 mm. This is far too much for the purpose of the present study, since all we are interested in is the determination of the location (coordinates of the centroid) and orientation (principal axes of inertia) of the rice grains. In order to reduce the computation time, the images will first be binned, that is each set of (say) 4×4×4 voxels will be replaced with a unique voxel, with average gray value (see Fig. 1 below for an illustration). 3D binning would usually require 3 uggly nested loops. There is, however, a much more pythonic way. This is the topic of the present post.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 2: acquisition of tomography images</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150310-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-02.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150310-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-02.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In the <a href="http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150223-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-01.html">first</a> instalment of this series, I briefly introduced orientational order in assemblies of anisotropic particles, and proposed an illustration based on synthetic microstructures. But what I really intend to do in this series is to show how orientational order can be quantified in a "real-life" sample, namely a packing of rice grains. This of course requires a 3D image of the packing. Fortunately, my lab (<a href="http://navier.enpc.fr/">Laboratoire Navier</a>) is the proud host of a <a href="http://navier.enpc.fr/Microtomographe,297">collaborative microtomography platform</a> and my former colleague Nicolas Lenoir --who was in charge of this instrument-- gave me the opportunity to scan my toy sample in december 2013.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation correlations among rice grains, part 1: introduction</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20150223-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-01.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20150223-Orientation_correlations_among_rice_grains-01.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2015</pubDate>
      <description>In this series, I will explore the notion of orientational order in random packings of anisotropic (flat or elongated), hard particles. By orientational order, I mean that particles which are close to each other tend to adopt the same orientation. This leads to strong /local/ anisotropy, while the packing may well be /globally/ isotropic; in particular, all orientations of single grains are equiprobable. Local orientational order is stronger when the volume fraction of particles, or their aspect ratio increases.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Blog!</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20141219-New_Blog.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20141219-New_Blog</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2014</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of "Parallel Programming with Python"</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20140813-Review_of_Parallel_Programming_with_Python.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20140813-Review_of_Parallel_Programming_with_Python.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2014</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The periodic Green operator for strains</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20140306-The_periodic_Green_operator_for_strains.html</link>
      <guid>The_periodic_Green_operator_for_strains.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 6 Mar 2014</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decomposition of transverse isotropic, fourth-rank tensors</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20140226-Decomposition_of_transverse_isotropic_fourth-rank_tensors.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20140226-Decomposition_of_transverse_isotropic_fourth-rank_tensors.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2014</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the double dot product</title>
      <link>http://sbrisard.github.io/posts/20140219-On_the_double_dot_product.html</link>
      <guid>posts/20140219-On_the_double_dot_product.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
